We are going to do a maha comparison of
probably the top four health insurance
products in the industry. I'm going to
talk about the product from ICIC, one
from Tata, one from HDFC and one from
NEA and we will see which product stands
up. I am a hardcore belieing that
everybody should have a health insurance
for themselves outside of what their
employer has provided just simply
because the employer insurance is
created considering employer's budget in
mind. They are not created considering
your needs. I will tell you more about
why you should not have depend on your
employer's insurance and why you should
just have a personal insurance later in
the video. Folks, welcome back to the
channel. My name is Nirj and I talk
about personal finance and credit cards
on this channel. I am an owner of
Holistic Prime Bill Private Limited. So,
let's move on and you know I'll share my
screen and we'll start the discussion.
Before we start the discussion folks,
understand that these are not
recommendations. This is just a
knowledge sharing session. If you are
interested in getting a personal health
insurance, reach out to me and I help
you get to one. Right? That's what we do
for all our clients in holistic prime
wealth as well. Uh now let us move on.
I'll start sharing my screen and start
seeing which products are probably the
good ones. All right. So this is you
know just the first page of the
presentation. We'll move to the second
page of the presentation. Now here you
can see I have put in the four products.
We are talking about HDFC Optima secure,
Tata Medicare Premier, ICA Eleant and
Diva Reassure 2.0 itenium plus. So the
first you know we will go step by step
and I will talk about each feature right
but the idea is that you know anytime
you talk about a health insurance
product the product should be
comprehensive in itself basically
meaning that you know whenever you are
hospitalized the out-ofpocket expenses
from your pocket so any money that you
pay from your pocket should be less than
5% of the total hospital bill that is
the whole idea when I talk about health
insurance products and when I you know
uh recommend it to my clients right so
rank limit Room rent limit is basically
they will say that you know you cannot
stay in a room of more than 1% of some
insured. Generally this is a limit which
is seen in employer policies right. So
why don't you not open your employer
policy and see what is a room and limit
as we you know discuss these different
features compare it with your employer
policies and see what is the feature
provided by your employer and is it
making sense or not and comment and tell
me what is the feature of your employer
policy and we'll discuss this right. So
first is the room rent limit right. So
room rent limit there should not be any
room rent limit at all. Basically if you
are admitted in a room which cost 20,000
rupees per month the insurance should
pay for the entire bill right but when
you stay in a room say which can say
that say single private AC room say for
example in ICA anyway it's a single
private AC room you have an option to
upgrade but if you're staying in a room
which is single private AC room what
going to happen is if you stay in a room
which costs 20,000 rupees but the limit
of single private AC room is only 10,000
rupees uh the 50% the total will will
get paid down. So if your hospital bill
is 5 lakh rupees, the insurer will only
pay 2.5 lakh rupees. That's why it
becomes very important that you know you
buy a policy without any room limit. So
up to some insured means there is no
room limit at all. ICIC elevate gives
you an option to upgrade. So we're
considering ICIC eleate you know better
to uh you know upgrade the you know move
to a no limit policy. Pre and post
hospitalization cover basically means
that you know when you get discharged
from any sort of hospitalization right
number of days before the
hospitalization and after the
hospitalization you will incur expenses
in the form of doctor fees consultations
you will you know spend money on
diagnostics and so on right all of those
things are also generally reimburseable
so ideally you should look at a policy
which gives you uh you know at least 60
days prehospization cover and 180 days
post hospitalization cover so all these
four give you that TATA gives you 60 and
90 days if the sum insured is less than
75 lakhs but if the summitur is more
than 75 lakhs if they give you 60 and
200 days so my personal policy is from
data wherein you know it's a 1 cr policy
so I have 60 and 200 days of cover
daycare treatment so you know daycare
treatment is generally not understood by
people right so daycare treatment
basically means that if you uh you know
there are a lot of treatments which
would take more than 24 hours earlier
right now those treatments are less take
less than 24 hours it can Say diialysis
for example, chemotherapy, right? So
these treatments are also covered in
your insurance policies and the list is
very very long actually. So you can
check the list for the respective
policies in the you know policy wording.
So day treatment is covered in all the
four product. Now let us move to the
next page. Uh doicillary treatment.
Doicillerary treatment means
hospitalization at home. This may happen
when hospitals you know are overcrowded.
Right? that time you may need to take
hospitalization at home or you need a
long-term hospitalization but you don't
want to stay in the hospitalization
doctor can recommend staying at home and
you know setting up a mini hospital at
home. So this was seen previously in
COVID where a lot of people were
hospitalized at home. So this is also
covered in all the four products thin
sum insured organ donor say if you have
to you know take an organ from somebody
else right so expenses incurred for that
organ donor will also be covered in this
policy modern treatments you know
something like surgeries done by robots
right this these things fall in modern
treatments only there is a one lakh
limit in modern treatment sub limit of
one lakh rupees but all others will
cover modern uh treatment up to the
submit no claim bonus again no claim
bonus is something which People consider
it as a very very important feature. I
personally you know recommend anyone
anybody to buy a health insurance for
the sum insured they need you to should
not be dependent on no claim bonus.
Okay. So HDFC Optima secure all these
four products have different no claim
bonuses. Let me take some time and
explain this to you. HDFC Optima secure
will give you the moment you purchase
this policy right the sum inured will
become two. So if you have you know
purchased a 10 lakhs policy it will
become 20 lakh rupees immediately on
purchase and if you don't make a claim
in the first two years this will become
4 lakh so 10 lakhs will become 40 lakh
rupees over and above that you will also
get 50% per year of no claim bonus on
the base sum insured up to 100%. Tata
Medicare it's a simple product 50% no
claim bonus per year up to 100%. ICA
elevate you know they don't call it no
claim bonus they call it loyalty bonus
and you know once acured this loyalty
bonus will not come down so if you
bought a 10 lakhs policy every year two
rupees will get added and your sum in
short will get increased by that amount
it will not come down reassure 2.0 has
two different products. So in Neabupa
reassure that they have platinum, bronze
and titanium, right? So in bronze there
is a 100% no claim bonus. Titanium
is,000% and inh platinum is 500. So what
does it mean? Every year you don't make
a claim in titanium it will go up by
100% every year. So if you bought a 10
lakh rupees policy it will you know
increase by 100% every year up to
1,000%. So if you 10 years old don't
make a claim it will go up to 1 cr
rupees. So HDFC special bonus we've
already discussed I'll not discuss it
again. Uh next is the restore benefit.
Restore benefit basically means that
that when you take a policy and uh you
got hospitalized right say you bought a
10 lakh rupees cover and you got
hospitalized you exhausted 8 lakh rupees
in the first hospitalization itself. Now
if you want to get hospitalized again
okay so restoration basically means that
the insurer will restore the limit again
back to 10 lakh rupees and you can you
know use the full 10 lakh rupees. So if
you can see HDFC says full plus partial
restore once per policy year for related
and unrelated illnesses. So basically in
the second claim it can be a related
illness, unrelatedness doesn't matter
you will get once per year. Data also
says the same thing but and also once
per year. ICIC you know says that you
know full plus partial restore
available this is unlimited number of
times right and same for NEA unlimited
number of times. Even Tata is unlimited
number of times and only in HDFC they
have once. Okay, Tata also it's one. So
this is the you know difference in
restore benefit. I personally you know
not a fan of restore benefit because the
industry itself has not yet seen how you
know the restore benefits work uh
practically. So we'll have to see over
time as the industry evolves we'll know.
So initial waiting period means
basically that if you bought a policy
right uh first 30 days nothing is
covered except for accident. This is
standard across all insurance companies.
So does not change. Pre-existing disease
waiting period basically means that if
you have already diagnosed with some
disease then the there will be a waiting
period for that disease. Right? So you
di diagnosed with diabetes. So for first
3 years or two years you will not be
able to get a treatment but tarta ICSA
and NEA all three have a benefit as have
an add-on wherein you can uh you know uh
take that add-on and you know cover
certain things from the 31st day which
is diabetes BP asma cholesterol these
four things are generally covered by the
insurers from uh the first year itself
so but you'll have to pay a higher
premium specific treatment waiting
period okay this is a very interesting
waiting period folks so this standard 24
months across all insurers. But if you
think about it, you know, earlier what
people used to do, uh they would get
say, you know, knee replacement needs to
be done or cataract needs to be done.
What they would do, they would go and
buy a health insurance and then
immediately make a claim. So health
insuranceers understood that people are
giving the system, right? That's why
they put up a cap on this. I mean they
have put up a waiting period on this and
there is a good list of treatments that
you cannot take. I'm putting it up on
the screen. uh cataract is included, ear
replacement, appendix, these kind of
things are included. Co-ayment basically
means that you know any uh say the
policy can say 10% co-ayment, right?
Check your employer's policy again. If
it says 10% co-ayment, which means that
the bill is 100 rupees, 10 10 rupees has
to be paid by you and balance will be
paid by insurer, right? So try to buy a
policy without any co-ayment. All the
four products do not have a co-ayment.
Health checkup is also something that
people you know love to have in their
policies. HDFC the maximum edge checkup
edge checkup cover is very very uh low
in this 2,000 for individuals 5,000 in
floater Tata Medicare premier it's
available cashless also and non-cashless
also it's inbuilt in the product uh so
there are different limits and tiers in
this if you have a policy of up to 75
lakh rupees 10,000 rupees is the limit
beyond the 20,000 and so on elevate it's
an optional cover you have to pay extra
premium for this 5,000 is a maximum
cover ne it's already included 5,000 is
the maximum cover for individuals and
10,000 for floater policies. Non-medical
expenses covered is very very important
guys. Basically you know gloves, PP
kits, oxygen masks, these things are
generally not covered in your insurance
policy. So make sure that you have this
included in any insurance that you buy.
Uh it is you know covered optional cover
in HDFC. Tata Medicare it's already
covered. I say elevate it's optional.
NEA it's already also optional. HDFC as
far as I remember it's not optional.
I'll put it up in the screen but you
have to definitely make sure that it's
covered. Maternity uh is covered by
default in Tata up to 50,000 rupees and
60,000 rupees for girl child but there
is going to be a four years waiting
period. HDFC and NEVA does not cover.
NEA has a separate product called NEA
aspire which covers maternity if you're
looking into that. ICA elevate covers
you have to buy it as an add-on but the
premiums will go up significantly.
premium will almost double in ICIC. So I
will not prefer it. Generally for
maternity I recommend that you use the
employer's cover because that is what
works best. Uh you can't really buy
insurance for any sort of planned claims
right. Health insurance come business.
It is a forprofit business. Do not you
know take it for granted. Road ambulance
air ambulance uh in air ambulance is
optional in HDFC secure and ICIC
elevate. uh it's covered up to 2.5 lakhs
in NEA and you know up to five lakhs in
Tata and so on. Road ambulance is also
covered. Tata has limits of 5,000 up to
50 lakhs some insured. Global cover
basically you know for any sort of
global treatments. Uh HDFC covers uh for
1 cr and above option. It's again
optional in HDFC. Tata by default covers
the the mandate is that the diagnosis
should happen in India and then you can
you know take a claim outside India. I
say also covers but it's an optional
treat optional add-on right I generally
don't recommend if I mean why will you
go outside take to take any sort of
treatment when everything is very very
good in India right so folks I guess
this is the end of the video a couple of
more things that I want to tell you ICA
elevate also gives you a credit score
based discount right so if your credit
score is very very good then you should
uh also look at ICAT because you will
get almost 15% discount and naupario 2.0
Titanium also has another feature
wherein the once you've paid the premium
right the premium will be frozen till
you make your first claim. So what does
this mean? Say for example you are 30
years old and you've paid 30,000 rupees
as your premium. You don't make a claim
for the next 10 years. The premium if
the company has not revised the premiums
for a you know a person of 30 years of
age your premium will not increase when
you turn 36 years old. Your premium will
only change if your uh if the company
revises the premium for somebody who is
30 years old, right? But if you don't
make a claim and company does not
changes the price chart, your premium
will not work. So that is also a gold
feature to consider. But it also makes
the product also very expensive, right?
So be mindful of that. Folks, I hope you
learned a lot from this video. Like I
said in the beginning, if you want to uh
you know buy a health insurance, reach
out to us and sharing my email in the
details below. And also you know do not
forget to like, share and subscribe.
Thank you for watching.